Guide to the Erl Bates papers, [ca. 1920-1960].
Bates, Erl papers, [ca. 1920-1960].
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Erl Bates papers, [ca. 1920-1960].
21-24-790
Erl Augustus Caesar Bates, 1889-1973.
1.6 cubic ft.
Correspondance, printed material, typescript reports, memoranda, newsletters, and pamphlets.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers include correspondence and memoranda pertaining to the background and passage of a state bill (1920) appropriating $10,000 to the College of Agriculture for Indian extension work and to the early progress of this work; correspondence and printed, mimeographed, and typescript reports, memoranda, newsletters, and pamphlets pertaining to the Cornell Indian Boards, Six Nations' Agricultural Society, Indian Farmers' Schools.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Erl Bates was a physician and advisor in Indian Extension at the New York State College of Agriculture at Cornell University.
Dr. Bates worked with New York county farm bureaus and home bureaus and the New York State Department of Education for the benefit of New York's Native Americans.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Papers include correspondence and memoranda pertaining to the background and passage of a state bill (1920) appropriating $10,000 to the College of Agriculture for Indian extension work and to the early progress of this work; correspondence and printed, mimeographed, and typescript reports, memoranda, newsletters, and pamphlets pertaining to the Cornell Indian Boards, Six Nations' Agricultural Society, Indian Farmers' Schools, Indian student attendance at Cornell University "short courses" in agriculture and home economics, the De Yen Twas Society, formed by Cornell Indian students to promote the welfare of the Six Nations, especially in agriculture and homemaking, the New York State Indian Welfare Society, the Indian Rights Association; Indian participation in Farm and Home Week, the New York State Fair, county fairs, and the Indian Fair; Bates' work with farm and home bureaus, and the New York State Education Department; the work of the Home Missions Council and the Council of Women for Home Missions on the reservation, the Cayuga-Seneca Land Case, 1920, the Syracuse Americanization League, Inc.; and lectures given by Bates to various groups. Also, typescript and mimeographed histories concerning New York Indians and the origins of various fruits cultivated in the U.S. by Indians, mimeographed and printed historical tour guides for various New York counties, Indian legends, a copy of Bates' book, Tell Me an Indian Story, and newspaper clippings.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bates, Erl Augustus Caesar, 1889-1973.; Cornell University--Students.; Cornell University. De Yen Twas Society.; Council of Women for Home Missions.; Home Missions Council of North America.; Indian Rights Association.; New York State Indian Welfare Society.; Six Nations' Agricultural Society.; Syracuse Americanization League.; University of the State of New York.
Subjects:
Agricultural exhibitions.; Agricultural extension work.; Home economics extension work.; Indians of North America--Agriculture.; Indians of North America--Education.; Indians of North America--History.; Indians of North America--Folklore.; Indians of North America--New York (State); Iroquois Indians.
Places:
Ithaca (N.Y.)--History.; Tompkins County (N.Y.)--History.; New York (State)--History.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Includes collection #21-24-1605.
CONTAINER LIST
- Collection 21-24-790
  - Correspondence (15 folders), 1851-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1-15)
  - History of the Indian Extension: copies - 16 a-f (7 folders) (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Indian Welfare Society, 1920, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Cayuga Indian Land Case (oil lease), 1921 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Indian Surveys (farms, homes, schools) (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Indian Students (applications, course schedules), 1921 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Indian Students: De Yen Twas Society, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Finances: Indian students, Farm Week (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Mimeographs Cornell Indian Boards, 1924-1933, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Mimeographs Cornell Indian Boards, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Manuscripts, typescript writings (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Notebook: Origins in Agriculture: Indians and Fruit (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Mimeographs: Indian Stories a-c (3 folders), 1932-1933, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Historical Tours a & b (2 folders), 1927-1928, 1930 and undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Newsclippings (incl. Ext. Ser. News) a-e (5 folders), 1919-1929 and undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Photographs (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Printed matter a-d (4 folders) (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Miscellaneous, 1950, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Tell Me an Indian Story by Bates, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Collection 21-24-1605
  - Photographs, typescripts, and printed matter relating to Indians; includes pamphlet written by A.G. Zeller on Samuel de Champlain's incursions against the Onondaga Nation (Box 21-24-1605 1-2)